Calvin Tomkins Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series I: Correspondence, 1964-2006
  Beginning in 1969 the files contain an increasing amount of personal correspondence. Tomkins received frequent letters from his two daughters, Anne (Trippy) Tomkins and Susan (Sue) Tomkins, and son, Spencer. The only correspondence from his first and second wives, Pat and Judy Tomkins, comes from periods following the demise of those relationships. Other family members, or long-time family friends, found in the correspondence files include his brother Frederick Tomkins, Jr., aunt and uncle Anne and T. Meade Baker, Laura Barclay, Roy C. Barker, and others.
  Other significant personal correspondents include Clare L. Spark, Kazuko Oshima, Nancy Rosen, Janie C. Lee, Lynn Hershman, Nancy Gillespie, Ren Weschler, Dona Guimaraes, Michael Neff, Robert Snyder, Grace Knowlton, Mary Allen, Ted Summer, Lucy Gray, and Sylvia and Edmund Morris, among others. Many of these people were fellow writers or artists and some were involved with Tomkins professionally. There are occasional notes and letters from people Tomkins wrote about or grew acquainted with during his work. These include Honoria Donnelly, Rosamond Bernier, Fanny Brennan, Christo and Jean-Claude, Michael Murphy (of the Esalen Institute), Siah Armajani, Victor and Sally Ganz, Philip Johnson, Paul and Julia Child, Hazel and Paul Strand, Jean and Dominique de Menil, and others. Few of these letters concern the actual research for the articles or seriously discuss Tomkins' work. Evidence also suggests that Tomkins developed a close acquaintance with R. Buckminster Fuller and planned to write Fuller's biography.
  Within each folder, materials are in loose reverse chronological order as Tomkins filed them. Typically the earliest materials for each year are letters received in mid-December of the previous year. It seems that a new folder was begun upon receipt of a new contract from The New Yorker.
  The folder descriptions below are not complete itemizations, but only highlight select items of significance.
  - Correspondence, 1964-1966; Contracts and correspondence concerning "The Lewis and Clark Trail" (later retitled "The Journals of Lewis and Clark") and The Bride and The Bachelors, 1966. 1 TLS Don Congdon-CT (3/30/1964) 1 TL CT-Don Congdon (3/27/1964) [both re: termination of his services as CT literary agent]. (Box 1, Folder I.1)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1965; Two unsigned letters, by "David Jones," to the Sunday Herald Tribune, disparaging the writings of Tom Wolfe. 1 ALS William Shawn-CT (2/18/1965) and other correspondence regarding TNY pay and fees. 1 TLS John Leggett (Harper & Row)-CT (12/10/1965) [re: CT's inquiry of possible book on George Kaufman]. (Box 1, Folder I.2)
  - Correspondence, 1966; Contract for article on Hugh Hefner 1 TL CT-unknown (n.d.) [re: observations on Leo Castelli] 1 TL CT-Helen K. Taylor, Viking Press (10/14/1966) [re: payments and mention of CT's activities] 1 TLS Hugh Hefner-CT (5/16/1966) 1 TL CT-The New York Times Magazine re: article on Leo Castelli (5/10/1966). (Box 1, Folder I.3)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1967; 1 TL R. Buckminster Fuller-John Huston (9/27/1967) [re: joint film proposal with CT] 1 TL CT-John Huston (10/9/1967) 1 TLS John (Jack) Macrae-George Trescher (12/21/1967) [re:Merchants and Masterpieces promotion] 1 TLS R. Buckminster Fuller-CT (9/27/1967) 1 TLS Lewis Allen-CT (7/24/1967) [re: response to CT film script] 1 TLS George Trescher-CT (8/25/1967) [re: initial suggestion of a book "project of significance" on the history of The Metropolitan Museum of Art]. (Box 1, Folder I.4)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1968; Contract for the publication of Eric Hoffer: An American Odyssey by C.P. Dutton (3/27/1968) 1 TL R. Buckminster Fuller-Milton Sperling (12/25/1968) 1 TL CT-The Century Club (3/22/1968) [re: recommendation of Jack Macrae for membership] Draft of contract from The Metropolitan Museum of Art for Merchants and Masterpieces TLS Paul M. Eisele-CT (11/1/1968) [re: appointment of CT as a director of stockholders for E.P. Dutton]. (Box 1, Folder I.5)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969; Incl. Final contracts and correspondence for Merchants and Masterpieces. (Box 1, Folder I.6)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1970; First references to Gerald and Sarah Murphy and CT's research and writing on their life as well as contract with Viking for the book. 2 TLS Andre Deutsch-CT [re: British printing of Living Well…] 1 TL R. Buckminster Fuller-CT (10/20/1970) Request for and draft of a recommendation letter endorsing R. Buckminster Fuller for a Nobel Prize (6/19/1970) 1 TLS Jean de Menil-CT (7/28/1970) 1 TLS Frank Kermode-CT (2/19/1970) 1 ALS Eric Hoffer-CT (1/22/1970). (Box 1, Folder I.7)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971; 1 TL CT-Cass Canfield, Harper & Row (11/3/1971) [re: interest in writing a biography of Edna St. Vincent Millay] 1 ALS Jean de Menil-CT (10/17/1971) 1 TLS Jann Wenner (ed. Rolling Stone Magazine)-CT (7/29/1971) 1 ALS Betty Dos Passos-CT (4/5/1971) 1 TLS Thomas Hoving-CT (1/14/1971) 1 ALS Jean de Menil-CT (10/17/1971) Contract with Andre Deutsch for British edition of Living Well…. (Box 1, Folder I.8)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972; 1 TLS Roger Angell-CT (3/7/n.y.) Contract for Brazilian edition of Living Well… Contract with Grossman Publishers for The Other Hamptons. (Box 1, Folder I.9)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973; Correspondence with various individuals concerning Fuller biography 1 TLS R. Buckminster Fuller-CT (9/25/1973) 1 TLS Georgia O'Keeffe-CT (7/13/1973) and correspondence with her assistant proposing TNY Profile 1 TLS Jacob Javits-CT (5/28/1973) 1 TLS Senator Edward Kennedy-CT (11/9/1973). (Box 1, Folder I.10)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974; 1 TLS Georgia O'Keeffe-CT (12/3/1974) 2 TL CT-Georgia O'Keeffe (3/19, 4/20/1974) 2 ALS Hazel and Paul Strand-CT (3/7/1974, n.d.) 1 ALS Margaret Barr (Mrs. Alfred H. Barr, Jr.)-CT (4/22/1974) 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (1/19/1974). (Box 1, Folder I.11)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1975; Various correspondence regarding The Scene… 4 TLS Michael (Mike) Murphy (The Esalen Institute)-CT (6/25, 5/5, 4/15, 12/1/n.y.) 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (1/20/1975) 1 TLS Georgia O'Keeffe-CT (2/7/1975) 1 TCS Georgia O'Keeffe-CT (3/11/1975) 1 TLS Philip Johnson-CT (1/8/1975) 1 TLS Julia Child-CT (1/2/1972). (Box 1, Folder I.12)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1977; 3 TLS Mike Murphy-CT (12/26, 6/28, 4/2, 1/14/1976) 1 TL CT-R. Buckminster Fuller re: possible biography (1/5/1977) 1 TLS Tatyana Grossman-CT (6/9/1976) Contract for contribution to Casuals, story entitled "The Master of Mill House". (Box 1, Folder I.13)
  - Correspondence, 1977; 1 TLS Mike Murphy-CT (12/3/n.y.) Family correspondence, note sheet of expenses, sympathy notes on the death of father (incl. Roger Angell) 2 ACS Claes Oldenburg-CT (4/27, 8/5/1977) 1 TLS Margaret Barr (Mrs. Alfred H. Barr, Jr.)-CT (n.d.) 1 TLS Christopher Buckley-CT (5/31/1977) 1 ALS Paul Goldberger-CT (5/26/1977) 1 ALS Philip Johnson-CT (n.d.) [re: congratulations on Profile]. (Box 2, Folder I.14)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1977; Correspondence and fan mail concerning article on Running Fence and the follow-up book on the same subject Note from agent indicating signing of contract with Doubleday for two unnamed works 1 TLS Dominique de Menil-CT (1/27/1977) 1 TLS Janie C. Lee-CT (1/6/1977) [on Jasper Johns' personal stationery, re: her stay on St. Martin with Johns]. (Box 2, Folder I.15)
  - Correspondence, 1978; Correspondence concerning book on Rauschenberg 1 ACS Christo-CT (n.d.) 1 ALS Pauline Kael-CT (3/10/n.y.) 1 ACS ["Note-o-gram"] John Cage-CT (7/9/1978) [re: Tomkin's possible interest in writing Cage biography]. (Box 2, Folder I.16)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978; 1 TLS Julia and Paul Child-CT (1/11/1978). (Box 2, Folder I.17)
  - Correspondence, 1979; 2 TLS Roger Angell-CT (11/26, 12/13/1979) 1 TLS R. Buckminster Fuller-CT (8/27/1979). (Box 2, Folder I.18)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1979; 1 ALS Robert Rauschenberg-CT (6/15/n.y.) 1 TLS Michael Murphy-CT (12/29/1978) 1 TLS Jean-Claude and Christo-CT (n.d). (Box 2, Folder I.19)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder I.20)
  - Correspondence, 1980; 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (6/10/n.y.) Many congratulatory notes on CT being appointed regular art reviewer at TNY. (Box 2, Folder I.21)
  - Correspondence, 1980; 1 ALS Nam Jun Paik-CT (n.d.) 2 ACS Robert Arneson-CT (8/5, 9/16/1980). (Box 2, Folder I.22)
  - Correspondence, 1981; 1 ALS Margaret Barr (Mrs. Alfred H. Barr, Jr.) (11/15/1981) [re: CT's commemoration of Barr] 1 ALS Hans Namuth-CT (8/11/1981) 1 TCS Paul and Julia Child-CT (8/2/1981) 1 ALS Holly Solomon-CT 7/28/1981) 1 TLS Robert Venturi-CT (7/20/1981) [re: membership in the Princeton Club]. (Box 3, Folder I.23)
  - Correspondence, 1981; 1 TLS Mike Murphy-CT (4/13/1981) 1 TLS Clare Boothe Luce-CT (4/4/1981) [re: correspondence with R. Buckminster Fuller]. (Box 3, Folder I.24)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981; 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (1/17/1981) 1 TLS Hans Namuth-CT (11/28/1980). (Box 3, Folder I.25)
  - Correspondence, 1982; 1 ALS Siah Armajani-CT (n.d.) 1 TLS Richard Bellamy-CT (n.d.) 1 ACS Merce Cunningham-CT (10/4/1982). (Box 3, Folder I.26)
  - Correspondence, 1982; 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (6/29/1982) 1 TLS Victor Ganz-CT (6/10/1982). (Box 3, Folder I.27)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982; 1 TLS Margaret Barr (Mrs. Alfred H. Barr, Jr.)-CT (n.d.) [re: creation of book of Alfred Barr's writings]. (Box 3, Folder I.28)
  - Correspondence, 1983; 1 ALS Romare Bearden-CT (12/7/n.y.) Various correspondence regarding abandonment of Fuller biography. (Box 3, Folder I.29)
  - Correspondence, 1983; 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (8/15/1983). (Box 3, Folder I.30)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 4, Folder I.31)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder I.32)
  - Correspondence, 1984; 1 ALS Romare Bearden-CT (12/4/n.y.) 1 TLS, et al. Pare Lorentz-TNY (1/10/1984) [re: inaccuracies in CT's Paul Strand Profile a decade previous]. (Box 4, Folder I.33)
  - Correspondence, 1984; 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (7/29/1984). (Box 4, Folder I.34)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1984; 1 TC Julia Child-CT (2/17/1984) 1 TLS Siah Armajani-CT (/22/1984). (Box 4, Folder I.35)
  - Correspondence, 1985; 1 ALS Siah Armajani (11/10/1985). (Box 4, Folder I.36)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 4, Folder I.37)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1985; 1 TL CT-Jacqueline Onassis (4/3/1985) [re: possible Profile] 1 ALS Merce Cunningham-CT (3/2/1985) 1 ALS Nam Jun Paik-CT (n.d.) 1 TLS Mike Wallace-CT (1/14/1984). (Box 5, Folder I.38)
  - Correspondence, 1986; 1 TLS Clement Greenberg-CT (11/11/1986) [incl. reference to David Smith's painted sculptures] 1 TLS Peter Halley-CT (10/10/1986). (Box 5, Folder I.39)
  - Correspondence, 1986; 2 TLS Louis Auchincloss-CT (8/1, 8/11/1986) [re: preparation of will] 1 ALS Merce Cunnningham-CT (8/8/n.y). (Box 5, Folder I.40)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986; 1 ALS Siah Armajani-CT (2/28/1986) 1 TL CT-Robert Lescher re: termination of agency (2/7/1986) Program for literary evening at the NYPL Brochure of employer contribution plan and trust from TNY, 1985. (Box 5, Folder I.41)
  - Correspondence, 1987; Beginning of references in correspondence to work on the Duchamp biography 1 ALS, 1 ACS Sally Ganz-CT (n.d., 11/29/1987) [re: memorial to Victor Ganz] 1 ACS Agnes Gund-CT (11/24/1987) 1 ACS Merce Cunningham-CT (9/15/1987). (Box 5, Folder I.42)
  - Correspondence, 1987; 1 ACS Siah Armajani-CT (7/26/1987) Correspondence regarding lending of CT's Donald Sultan work to the Chicago Museum of Contemporary Art (and for retail sale of its reproduction) 1 ACS, 1 ALS DK-CT addressed from "Paola" to "Francesca" (8/12, 8/24/1987) 1 TL CT-Jacqueline Onassis (5/27/1987) [re: particulars of new edition of Merchants and Masterpieces.] (Box 5, Folder I.43)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1987; 1 ACS Carl Andre(?)-CT (1/17/1987). (Box 5, Folder I.44)
  - Correspondence, 1988; 1 TLS Henry Geldzahler-CT re: Century Assoc. membership (n.d.) 1 TL CT-Jack Macrae [re: schedule of Duchamp research indicating final draft to be ready late summer of 1989] 1 TLS Walter Annenberg-CT (5/31/1988) [re: CT's article on The Irises by van Gogh]. (Box 6, Folder I.45)
  - Correspondence, 1988; 1 ALS (photocopy) CT-Walter Keep (headmaster professor, Berkshire School) (n.d.) from CT's freshman year at Princeton. (Box 6, Folder I.46)
  - Correspondence, 1989; 1 TLS Jerome Gold-CT (9/26/1989) [re: arranging interview with Madame Juliette Man Ray for Duchamp biography]. (Box 6, Folder I.47)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 6, Folder I.48)
  - Correspondence, 1989; 1 ALS, 2 TCS Sally Ganz-CT (n.d., 1/16/1989, n.d.) 1 ACS Jeanne-Claude and Christo-CT (1/2/1989). (Box 6, Folder I.49)
  - Correspondence, 1990; 1 TLS Philip Johnson-CT (10/31/1990). (Box 6, Folder I.50)
  - Correspondence, 1990; 1 TCS Clement Greenberg-CT (6/19/1990) 1 ALS Siah Armajani-CT (5/10/1990). (Box 6, Folder I.51)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 6, Folder I.52)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1991; 1 ALS Sally Ganz-CT (n.d.) 1 TLS Daniel J. Boorstin-CT (12/14/1990). (Box 6, Folder I.53)
  - Correspondence, 1992; 1 TL CT-Matta re: request to do Profile (7/10/1992) Unsigned, undated letter to "Anne and Meade" (aunt and uncle) consisting of memories of CT at six years old. (Box 6, Folder I.54)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1992; 2 ACS Jeanne-Claude and Christo-DK and CT (n.d). (Box 7, Folder I.55)
  - Correspondence, 1993; 1 ACS Jeanne-Claude and Christo-CT and DK (9/15/1993) 1 TLS Siah Armajani-CT and DK (9/19/1993) 1 ALS Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis-CT and DK (8/7/n.y.) [re: galleys of Liberman book]. (Box 7, Folder I.56)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1993; 1 TLS Richard Avedon-CT (6/17/1993) 1 ACS Siah Armajani-CT and DK (1993). (Box 7, Folder I.57)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 7, Folder I.58)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1995; 1 TLS Siam Armajani-CT and DK (11/25/1995). (Box 7, Folder I.59)
  - Correspondence, 1996; Large amount of responses to the publication of Duchamp: A Biography 1 TLS Leonard Lauder-CT and DK (12/16/1996) 1 TLS Richard Avedon-CT (12/10/1996). (Box 7, Folder I.60)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 7, Folder I.61)
  - Correspondence, 1996; Packet of drawings and letter from illustrator Jon Sarkin. (Box 7, Folder I.62)
  - Correspondence, 1997; Handmade booklet and other drawings by Jon Sarkin. (Box 7, Folder I.63)
  - Correspondence, 1997; 1 TL CT-"Ms. Johnson" re: recollection of first meeting and continued association with Marcel Duchamp (3/26/1997) 2 TLS Patterson Sims-CT re: formation of MoMA archives, library and research committee (2/10, 2/28/1997) 1 TLS Agnes Gund-CT re: support for arts oriented television channel (2/13/1997) Correspondence regarding interview on Duchamp for the BBC. (Box 8, Folder I.64)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997; 1 TL CT-Chris Granlund re: BBC Duchamp research (1/27/1997) and further correspondence on the subject 1 ACS David Salle-CT (n.d.) Undated drawing from Jon Sarkin Articles and correspondence from sculptor Casimer Michalczyk detailing his life and career. (Box 8, Folder I.65)
  - Correspondence, 1997; Corr. from the MoMA and the Getty each discussing possibility of receiving CT's papers. (Box 8, Folder I.66)
  - Correspondence, 1997; Correspondence and agenda regarding MoMA library advisory committee, BBC documentary on Rauschenberg, BBC documentary on the New Yorker 1 TLS CT-Rodrigo de Zayas re: research for Profile on Philippe de Montebello (7/20/1997) Collage from Jon Sarkin. (Box 8, Folder I.67)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 8, Folder I.68)
  - Correspondence, 1998-1999; Correspondence regarding Modern Library edition of Living Well…. (Box 8, Folder I.69)
  - Correspondence, 1998; 1 TLS Sylvie Boissonnas [sister of Dominique de Menil]-CT (5/15/1998). (Box 8, Folder I.70)
  - Correspondence, 1998; Numerous copies of fax transmissions and letters from CT on various matters such as blurb copy for Francis Naumann's Duchamp book, the paperback edition of CT's Duchamp book, requests for review copies of books, congratulations to Renzo Piano on the Pritzker Prize, etc. (Box 8, Folder I.71)
  - Correspondence, 1999; 1 TLS Edmund Morris-CT (11/24/1999) 1 TL CT-Edmund Morris (11/14/1999) Request from the Hermitage, and CT's response, for his opinion of the twenty-five most important artworks of the 20th century. (Box 9, Folder I.72)
  - Correspondence, 1999; 1 ALS Sydney Biddle-CT and DK (n.d.) 1 TL CT-Paul Auster (7/20/1999) 1 TLS CT-Damien Hirst re: arranging meetings with Hirst for Profile (4/16/1999). (Box 9, Folder I.73)
  - Correspondence, 1999; 1 ALS Leonard Lauder-CT (n.d.) 1 ALS Glenn Lowry-CT (2/11/1999). (Box 9, Folder I.74)
  - Correspondence, 2000; 1 TL (fax) Nam Jun Paik-Paula Cooper [re: missing CT's birthday] 1 TLS Jasper Johns-CT (12/15/2000) [re: regrets on missing CT's 75th birthday dinner]. (Box 9, Folder I.75)
  - Correspondence, 2000; 1 ACS Cindy Sherman (signed "Cindy and Frieda")-CT (n.d.) Packet of material from Jean-Jacques Lebel, (2/8/2000) rebutting CT's Profile of Ileana Sonnabend (in which Lebel was mentioned). (Box 9, Folder I.76)
  - Correspondence, 2001; Exchange between Bob Rosen and CT [re: Duchamp, and the absence of a discussion of women in CT's book] (6/4, 7/12/201). (Box 9, Folder I.77)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2001; 1 ALS Annette de la Renta-CT re: turning down his request for a Profile (4/23/n.y.) 1 TLS Glenn Lowry-CT [re: invitation to dinner at Century Club] (1/16/2001). (Box 9, Folder I.78)
  - Correspondence, 2002; Responses to article "Can Art be Taught?" and Profile on Richard Serra (including 1 TLS facsimile from Richard Avedon), correspondence from the MoMA Library Council, inquiries from researchers and invitations to attend or participate in various events and projects. (Box 10, Folder I.79)
  - Correspondence, 2002; Further responses to "Can Art be Taught?", correspondence from MoMA Library Council and discussion of archive (including a note from Glen Lowry). (Box 10, Folder I.80)
  - Correspondence, 2003-2004; Includes correspondence regarding the small exhibition of CT's papers at MoMA, program from memorial tribute to Kirk Varnedoe. (Box 10, Folder I.81)
  - Correspondence, 2003; Includes readers' responses to Profile on Matthew Barney and other articles. (Box 10, Folder I.82)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2005; Reader's responses to the autobiographical sketch, "Summer Afternoon," and Profile on Maurizio Cattelan. (Box 10, Folder I.83)
  - Correspondence, 2004; Includes series of correspondence between writer Edmund Morris and CT, featuring the trading of bawdy limericks, letters from Hans Haacke, Jacqueline Matisse Monnier, and a correspondence inviting CT to participate in Ric Burn's documentary on Andy Warhol. (Box 10, Folder I.84)
  - Correspondence, 2005; Includes 1 TLS Jeanne-Claude & Christo-CT (7/10/2005) 1 TLS facsimile James Turrell and Kyung-Lim Lee-CT and DK (7/28/2005). (Box 10, Folder I.85)
  - Correspondence, 2005; Includes 1 ACS Jeanne-Claude & Christo-CT (n.d). (Box 11, Folder I.86)
  - Correspondence, 2005; Includes 1 ACS Maurizio Cattelan and Massimiliano Gione-CT and DK (n.d). (Box 11, Folder I.87)
  - Correspondence, 2006; Reader responses to Profile on Jasper Johns and article on MoMA, including notes from Robert Storr, Jeanne-Claude & Christo, Sylvia and Edmund Morris, Roger Angell, Sam Varnedoe, and others. Also includes signed contract for services between DK and CT and TNY for 2006-2007. (Box 11, Folder I.88)
  - Correspondence, 2005-2006; Includes 1 ALS Jeff Wall-CT (4/3/[2006]) [re: lack of interest from TNY for article on Wall]; also correspondence regarding CT receiving the Clark Prize for Excellence in Arts Writing, reciprocal correspondence between CT and Edmund Morris discussing Duchamp and Rauschenberg, and materials related to CT's participation in events surrounding the exhibition Robert Rauschenberg: Combines at The Metropolitan Museum of Art. (Box 11, Folder I.89)
- Series II: Major New Yorker Articles, 1961-2006
  Tomkins segregated the files for his major articles apart from his other writing files. They were kept in rough chronological order; that order has been refined here. The files were split into two parts. Subseries II.A contains the research files of loose notes, published materials, correspondence, and ephemera relating to the subject. Subseries II.B contains the research binders of original material and interview notes and transcripts Tomkins assembled for nearly every article. More detailed descriptions of the contents are below.
  - Subseries II.A: Research Files, 1961-2006
    These files represent materials produced and acquired for the writing of major articles for The New Yorker magazine between 1962 and 2004. While the majority of these articles were published under the rubric "Profiles," there are articles published under other departments, including "A Reporter at Large," "Annals of Law," "Onward and Upward with the Arts," "The Skyline," and "Department of Education." Which department an article was published under seems to have been a decision reached after the article was written; many articles, such as the one on Frank Gehry, were labeled as Profiles in manuscript form but published as another department. While most Profiles concern individuals there is one, "The Black People of Bridgehampton," that concerns a community. Many of the articles published as "Onward and Upward…" concern individuals and seem no different in content than Profiles. There is evidence in these files of the growth and change of articles from their initial conception. "Irises," an article on the meteoric growth of the art market at auction, began as a Profile of David Nash while the article on dyslexia, "The Last Skill Acquired," apparently went through many changes of focus on its way to publication. But the articles resemble each other in their length and in the research process Tomkins used to write them.
    The materials in these folders are weighted toward previously published materials. They include extensive news clippings, magazine articles, tear sheets, offprints and photocopies, pamphlets, brochures, gallery and exhibition catalogs and ephemera. Almost every group of folders for an article includes tear sheets or photocopies of the printed article from The New Yorker. Many folders also contain materials postdating publication. Most often these are news clippings and articles such as obituaries. Original materials include correspondence with the article subjects, both prior to and after publication, and correspondence from readers, many of which dispute facts in the articles; the latter are often accompanied by official magazine responses. Overall the correspondence present in this series is more substantive and relevant to Tomkins' research than that present in the previous series. Handwritten research notes are scattered throughout, mostly consisting of lists of interview contacts and biographical and interview notes. Most of the folder groups also include a typescript draft of the article with hand edits and amendments; the date of these drafts is noted when present. The hand edits are minimal and are likely from copy editors at the magazine although there is evidence that some interview subjects reviewed the articles before publication. A few folders contain multiple typescript drafts of different dates.
    While the contents of the separately organized research binders are discussed below, some of their contents have filtered into these folders or are duplicated here. Such materials include interview transcripts, summaries and glosses, notes of time spent with the interview subjects (often referred to as the "log"), and index pages for the binders. These materials are described more fully in the next series.